--==聖城家園SCG字幕組 http://hd.cnscg.com/==--
協調: 影子
翻譯: Uriana  戴蜀
校對: 有個飯團
註明: 以藍光原盤SUP英文字幕為基準
修正錯別字和時間軸  增補遺漏台詞及歌詞
( 非傲慢即偏見 @Sub HD )
西 西 裏 的 美 麗 傳 說
今天下午五點鐘
This afternoon at 5:00,
元首(貝尼托·墨索里尼)將向全國發表聲明
Il Duce (Benito Mussolini) will speak to the nation!
屆時每個人都必須打開收音機
You are ordered to turn your radios on!
有無線電設備或無線留聲機的人
All of you who have radio sets and radio gramophones...
也都必須打開
are ordered to turn them on.
墨索里尼將向
Mussolini will speak to...
全意大利發表聲明
all Italians!
法西斯政府已允許你們
You are authorized by order of the Fascist government...
獻給我的父親
To My Father
暫停工作  今天下午五點  元首將向全國發表聲明
to interrupt your work. This afternoon at 5:00, Il Duce will speak to the nation.
第一次見她時  我十二歲半
I was twelve and a half when I saw her for the first time.
雖然我記性不好  但這件事我記得很清楚
And my mind plays tricks on me, I remember it well.
同一天  墨索里尼向英法宣戰
That day, Mussolini declared war on France and Great Britain...
而我有了人生中第一輛自行車
and I got my first bicycle.
車架是英國的  齒輪是德國的
The frame is British, the gears are German,
踏板是法國的
the pedals are French,
剎車是哪兒的  我忘了
and the brakes are from... I forget.
不過鏈條是西西里本地的  別忘了多抹油
But the chain is Sicilian... always keep it greasy.
你確定這安全嗎
Are you sure it's safe?
我也有新車
I have new bikes too.
老米  這都宣戰了  誰還買得起新車
Mimi, we're at war. Who can afford a new bicycle?
戰士們
Fighting men,
陸軍  海軍  空軍
on land, on sea and in the air,
黑衣革命黨
Black shirts of the revolution,
意大利的所有人
men and women of Italy...
以及阿爾巴尼亞王國
and the Kingdom of Albania, hearth is...
此決定
The hour...
即刻生效
of decisions from which
永不反悔
there is no return.
皮諾  你覺得這螞蟻知道自己要死了嗎
Pino, think this ant knows he's dead meat?
誰知道呢
Who knows?
如果他跟你一樣  那肯定是什麼都不知道了
If he's like you, he doesn't know shit.
此次宣戰聲明
The declaration of war...
已被送達外交大使手裏
has already been delivered to the ambassadors.
從痛苦中解脫出來  我視瑪麗之子為上帝
I'm free from misery. Mary's son is my Lord.
嘿
Hey, guys!
夠幸運的你
Lucky bastard.
- 他這輛自行車是新的  - 真好看
- He got a new bicycle! - Man, she's beautiful!
手工定制的  跟賽車一樣
Custom-made, just like the racers.
- 現在你跟我們一樣  是個男人了  - 那我能加入你們嗎
- Now you're a man, like us. - So I can join the gang?
- 阿戈斯蒂諾先生  - 我同意
- "Don Agostino"? - Okay by me.
- 尼古拉先生  - 讓他加入吧
- "Don Nicola"? - I'd let him in.
- 托尼諾先生  - 可以
- "Don Tonino"? - Sure.
- 你呢  薩先生  - 我不想讓小屁孩摻合進來
- And you, "Don Sasa"? - I don't want some kid poking into our business.
- 為什麼  你們在幹嘛  - 能閉嘴嗎
- Why? What are you doing? - Can you keep your mouth shut?
她來了
She's coming!
怎麼了
What's going on?
想加入我們的話  就閉嘴看
If you wanna be one of us, just shut up and watch.
- 她是誰  - 我們的新拉丁語老師  那個聾子的女兒
- Who is she? - The deaf guy's daughter, our new Latin teacher.
- 她叫什麼  - 多美的屁股啊
- What's her name? - What a wonderful ass!
如果能和她共度良宵  我什麼都願意
What I wouldn't give for an hour with her!
- 可惜她結婚了  - 如果她沒結
- Too bad she's married. - If she weren't...
她叫什麼
What's her name?
瑪蓮娜  克斯特庫托村裏的第一美臀
Malena, the most beautiful ass in Castelcuto.
太陽比月亮要大
The sun is bigger than the moon.
拉丁語念作  太陽比月亮要大
Or "Sol maior est quam lunam."
我能搞你女兒嗎  你這個老聾子
Can I screw your daughter, you deaf old fart?
好吧  你快點
Yes, but hurry.
比起錢財我更愛誠實
I love honesty more than wealth.
"Magis diligo onestatem quam divitias."
Or "Magis diligo onestatem divitiis."
- 七個大拇指長  - 七個半
- Seven thumbs long! - Seven and a half thumbs!
- 我的簡直就是火箭筒  - 八個
- Mine's a bazooka! - I got eight!
八個也沒什麼的  只能給女人撓癢癢
Eight is nothing! That's just tickling a woman.
一  二  三加二是五  加二得七  再加二得九
One, two... three and two is five, two is seven and two is nine.
魚雷
Torpedo!
我的武器會把瑪蓮娜炸翻的
My submarine will rip Malena in half!
有一次我翹了課  路過瑪蓮娜的房子
Once I skipped school and went by Malena's house.
她在窗邊  喊我過去
She was at the window, and she called out to me.
我以為她要讓我幫忙買煙
I thought she wanted me to get her some cigarettes.
我去拿錢  結果她的睡袍散了
I went up for the money, and her robe fell open.
就那樣  赤身裸體的站在那裏
And there she was... naked as the day she was born.
我的天  她一定是故意誘惑我的
Holy shit! She did it on purpose to excite me.
我太傻了  早知道有機會就上了
I was an idiot. I should have jumped at the chance.
再給我一次機會  我肯定操翻她
If it happens again, I'll bang her brains out.
首先  她會戒煙的  她已經知道你沒色膽了
She'd quit smoking first. She knows you've got no balls.
你個小崽子  你都在這兩小時了
You little runt, you've been here for two hours...
還不量量自己的尺寸
and you still haven't measured yourself.
快量
Measure it!
一  二
One, two,
三  四  五
three, four, five...
只數到六
Only six!
你知道怎麼形容穿短褲的小孩嗎
You know what they say about a kid in short pants?
褲子很短  雞巴更短
Short pants: Short dick!
去你的  我的大拇指有你兩倍大
Fuck off. My thumbs are twice as big as yours!
扯淡
Bullshit!
- 混蛋  你說誰的雞巴最大  哼  - 你的
- Who's got the biggest dick now, runt? - You do!
我是元首  沒人比我更大
No, I am II Duce! Nobody's bigger than me!
- 喔  雷納多翹課了  - 噓
- Ooh. Renato's skipping school. - Shh!
你  過來  幫我買盒煙
You, come here! I need some cigarettes.
你想要什麼煙
What cigarettes do you want?
馬其頓  上品
Macedonia Extra.
我記得這條褲子很合身  是你爸的
I remember this suit very well. It's your father's.
是我二十年前做的  現在看起來還是嶄新的
I sewed it 20 years ago, and it still looks brand-new.
他只在結婚的時候穿過  他想留著葬禮穿
He only wore it to his wedding. He wants to keep it for his funeral.
如果他穿著這個下葬  那就直接進天堂了
If he's buried in this suit, he'll go straight to heaven!
我爸還年輕
My father's still young.
而你也太年輕了  不能穿長褲
And you're too young for long pants.
我沒問你的意見  先生
I didn't ask for your opinion, sir.
- 他知道嗎  - 他當然知道
- Does he know about this? - Of course he does!
你個小壞蛋  這是怎麼搞的
You little scoundrel, what the hell is this?
給我過來  你竟然還翹課
Come here, mister. So you want to skip school?
當然了  這個年紀誰不逃學
Fine. Who didn't at your age?
- 別打他  - 我自有分寸
- Leave him alone! - I know what I'm doing.
你還讓你朋友打了一頓
And you let your friends beat you up.
我當年像你這麼大的時候  只有我揍別人的份
Even though when I was your age, I'd beat my friends up!
但你竟敢從你爸這裏偷褲子
But stealing trousers from your father...
還拿去改了自己穿  這就大錯特錯了
and getting them altered for yourself is just plain wrong.
可是爸爸  你不明白
But, Papa, you don't understand!
不明白  誰讓你說話了
Understand? Who said you could speak?
我現在還穿短褲  很丟臉
I'm ashamed to wear short pants!
燈籠褲呢  那基本算是長褲了
What about knickers? They're almost long pants!
夠了  他還小啊
Enough! He's still a child!
我要去告訴黨支部書記  你不讓我參加法西斯訓練
I'll tell our party secretary you won't let me go to the Fascist exercises!
我們定個約
Let's make a deal.
哪天有人把咱偉大的領袖打爆頭
The day someone cracks the skull of "Our Great Leader,"
你就能穿長褲了
then you'll get long pants.
你發誓
Swear it.
這麼年輕漂亮的女人獨身一人  真是罪過
A beautiful young woman all alone here. It's a crime.
- 他說誰呢  - 瑪蓮娜·斯克迪亞  尼諾的性感老婆
- Who's he talking about? - Malena Scordia, Nino's sexy new wife.
她枕邊一定有別人  肯定的
She must have somebody on the side... it's inevitable!
- 十五號  - 我
- Number fifteen! - Me.
尼諾從她鎮裏把她和她那耳朵不好使的爸爸一起接來
Right. Nino brings her from her village with her ailing father.
結果一個月之後  砰  尼諾上戰場了
And then a month later... boom... Nino's called to the war.
誰敢打賭她不跟別人睡
Who here wants to bet she's sleeping all alone?
我才不打呢
Not me!
為什麼我不能跟他們坐一起
Why don't you let me sit with the others?
你還太小  不能坐大人的椅子
You're too young to sit in the adult chair.
♪ 但是愛不會 ♪
♪ But love, no, ♪
♪ 我的愛不會 ♪
♪ My love cannot... ♪
♪ 像凋落的玫瑰一樣隨風而逝 ♪
♪ ...dissolve itself in the wind with the roses. ♪
♪ 熾熱之愛永不枯萎 ♪
♪ So strong that it will not surrender. ♪
♪ 我會呵護這份愛 ♪
♪ I will watch over it, ♪
♪ 我會捍衛這份愛 ♪
♪ I will defend it... ♪
♪ 使其免受外界荼毒 ♪
♪ ...from all those poisoned hidden dangers... ♪
♪ 這份執著深扎我心 ♪
♪ ...that would want to rip from the heart. ♪
♪ 伶人的愛啊 ♪
♪ Poor love! ♪
♪ 也許你會離開 ♪
♪ Maybe you will go, ♪
♪ 投入她人懷抱尋覓慰藉 ♪
♪ to look for other women's caress. ♪
♪ 憐人的我啊 ♪
♪ Poor me! ♪
♪ 如果你返鄉歸來 ♪
♪ And if you come back... ♪
♪ 那時你會發現良辰美景已逝  佳人遲暮 ♪
♪ you will find every beauty already faded in me.♪
♪ 但是愛不會 ♪
♪ But love, no, ♪
♪ 我的愛不會像我的金髮一樣褪色消弭 ♪
♪ My love cannot fade away like the gold in my hair. ♪
♪ 忠貞不悔  至死不渝 ♪
♪ Until I die it will be alive in me. ♪
♪ 我的心中只有你 ♪
♪ Only for you. ♪
孩子啊  你不知道歌名叫什麼  我怎麼幫你
But, son, if you don't know the title, how can I help you?
就是曲調優美  非常浪漫
It's that pretty, romantic one...
但是愛不會  你怎麼不早說
Ma L'Amore No. Why didn't you say so?
十塊錢  去收銀台付錢吧
Ten lire. Pay at the cashier's.
- 你不試聽一下嗎  - 為什麼
- Don't you test it? - What for?
- 也許壞了呢  - 這是全新的
- It might be defective. - It's brand-new!
瑪蓮娜小姐  我這顆燃燒的心  為你寫了無數封信
Miss Malena, this heart of mine, on fire, has written so many letters,
但我卻無法鼓起勇氣寄給你
and if I didn't have the courage to send them to you,
只是因為不想傷害你
it was only because I didn't want to do you harm.
如果我寄出了這一封  請見諒
So forgive me if I dare to send you this one.
鎮上有很多流言蜚語
I want you to know that this town has many gossips...
惡意中傷你  說你有個情夫
who say bad things about you... that you have a secret lover.
我知道這不是真的  你沒有任何人
I know it's not true. You don't have anyone.
你丈夫走後  你心中唯一的男人  只有我
After your husband, the only man in your life is me.
我得走了  明天學校見
I have to go. I'll see you at school tomorrow.
再見
So long!
別迷路了
Don't get lost!
律師大人  你把報紙拿反了
Mr. Lawyer! Your newspaper's upside down!
多管閒事
Mind your own fucking business!
早上好  瑪蓮娜夫人  你還好嗎  令尊可好
Good morning, Signora Malena. Are you well? How is your father?
看夠了吧  演出結束  她走了
The show's over! She's gone now!
我忘帶鑰匙了
I forgot the key.
看來大家說的是真的了
So it's true what people say!
你怎麼了  你看起來好奇怪
What's the matter with you? You look so strange.
你用謊言困住了我
You've poisoned me with your lies.
什麼謊言  我都沒跟你說過話
What lies? I've never spoken to you.
我早就知道  你是個放蕩的女人
I knew it from the start... you're a loose woman.
可是我沒做錯任何事啊
But I've never done anything wrong.
騙子  我一直騎車跟蹤你
Liar! I've been following you on my bicycle!
- 我知道你去了哪兒  我什麼都知道  - 不
- I know where you went. I know everything! - No!
- 律師 還有牙醫  - 不  雷納多  我只愛你
- The lawyer, the dentist! - No, Renato, I love only you!
騙子
Liar!
- 阿莫羅索  - 到
- Amoroso. - Here!
- 卡裏  - 到
- Cali. - Here!
- 科斯坦薩  - 到
- Costanza. - Here!
教授  我能把雞巴塞到瑪蓮娜的奶子中間嗎
Professor, can I put my dick between Malena's tits?
我能塞進她嘴裏嗎
Can I put mine in her mouth?
我能塞到她大腿深處嗎
Can I put mine between her legs?
好吧  但只能一個一個來
Okay, but one at a time!
你給鏈條上過油嗎
Do you spit instead of oiling it?
沒有  我上的食用油
No. I use cooking oil.
如果你來這兒  我會給你一些油
If you come, I will give it to you.
得用機械油  傻瓜  或是潤滑油  那更好
Used machine needs oil, fool. Or grease, which is better.
你知道潤滑油嗎  它能讓鏈條保持順溜
Do you know grease? Keep over the chain slippery!
她為什麼不嫁個她們鎮上的人
Why didn't she marry someone from her own village?
肯定是沒人要她
I'm sure no one wanted her.
聽說她是個裁縫
They say she's a seamstress.
但是她也太粗野了
But she's so vulgar.
我兒子說她看起來好假
My son says she looks fake.
我丈夫說  就算有三米長的桿子  他都不會碰她
My husband says he wouldn't touch her with a ten-foot pole.
波塔男爵的情婦就好得多
The Baron Bonta's mistress is much nicer.
至少吉娜不遮遮掩掩的
At least Gina does everything in the open.
男爵一周來睡她一次  然後就回巴勒莫(西西里首府)
The baron screws her once a week and then goes back to Palermo.
瑪蓮娜裝得這麼清高  以為我們不知道她都幹了什麼
Malena acts so superior. Like we don't know what she's up to.
等著瞧吧  她會有報應的
Wait and see. She'll get hers.
軍隊總部發出聲明
The headquarters of the armed forces communicates...
我們勇敢無敵的戰士們帶領著
Our brave and invincible Fighting men have delivered a powerful blow...
盟軍殺人不見血的武器
to the faceless war machine unleashed by the Allies.
為了確保戰場上
In order to ensure the continued strength and vitality...
人力物力的供給
of our forces at the front,
所有市民的工資  將再次被延遲發放
all payment of civic pensions... will again be postponed...
- 好了  - 謝謝
- It's ready. - Thank you.
你會變瞎的
You will go blind!
瑪蓮娜
Malena.
右列  向前看
Right rank! Eyes front!
舉起手臂來  重複
Arms out, arms high, in quick succession!
一  二  一  二
One, two! One, two!
聽說了嗎  瑪蓮娜的丈夫死了
Have you heard? Malena's husband was killed.
可以追瑪蓮娜了
Malena is available!
克斯特庫托村的同胞們
Comrades of Castelcuto,
今日我們聚集於此
we are gathered here today...
為這可歌可泣的噩耗
to share in the tragic but honorable mourning...
表示沉重地哀悼
which has struck our town.
哀悼尼諾·斯克迪亞上尉
To express our deepest condolences...
並致以我們最深沉的弔唁
for the loss of Lt. Nino Scordia...
他英雄般的死在  北非的戰場上
heroically killed in action... in Northern Africa...
也對他的遺孀瑪蓮娜表示慰問
and to his bride Maddalena,
可惜她太過傷心  無法出席
who, stricken with grief, unfortunately isn't here with us.
- 她已經開始勾搭別人了  - 找別人暖床
- She's already out looking! - She'll need a warm bed now!
但我們的心和她在一起  因為西西里的女人
But she is with us in spirit, because Sicilian women...
守得住艱辛  做得出犧牲
with their hardships, with their sacrifices,
誓死與戰士們共前進
march shoulder to shoulder with Fighting men!
在座的市民們為了保衛祖國所付出的一切不會被忘記
Of our fellow citizen in defense of his country was not a useless
凱迪上尉好帥
Lt. Cadei is so handsome.
誰釣到他就幸運了
A lucky girl will catch him!
帶領我們走向法西斯帝國的最終勝利
That will carry us to the final victory of the Fascist Empire!
勝利萬歲
For Victory!
元首萬歲
Long live II Duce!
從現在起  我會一直在你身邊
From now on I'll be at your side.
直到永遠  我保證
Forever. I promise.
只要給我些時間讓我長大
Just give me time to grow up.
現在她要找情人了吧
Now she'll take a lover for sure.
一旦上了床  可就沒回頭路了
Once in the sack, there's no looking back!
她肯定懂  她都二十七歲了
She knows that. She's 27 years old.
她的技術一定很好
She knows her way around the block!
牙醫庫西馬諾都為她瘋狂了
Cusimano, the dentist, has gone crazy for her.
有一天  她路過  他看得呆了
One day he was distracted as he walked by...
結果拔錯了一顆好牙
and pulled a healthy tooth instead of the rotten one!
不管那牙醫了  為什麼最近都沒見到她
Dentist or not, why haven't we seen her lately?
她太忙了唄
Guess she's too busy!
聽說她跟卡塔尼亞的一個
They say she's fooling around with a shopkeeper in Catania...
反動的老闆鬼混
with subversive tendencies.
也有人說是牙醫庫西馬諾
Some say Cusimano, the dentist.
- 有家室的人  太丟臉了  - 生下來就是個婊子
- A family man. It's disgraceful! - When you're a born whore...
聽說牧師收到各種匿名信
I hear the priest has received anonymous letters...
說她情人是誰是誰
saying her lover is this man, that man.
人民的聲音就是上帝的聲音
The voice of the people is the voice of God!
我沒法跟別人傾訴我的困擾
I can't talk to anyone about my personal problems.
太私密了
They're too intimate.
你看起來人很好  我就對你說吧
But you seem nice. I'd like to confide in you.
每天我都來給你點一支蠟燭
Every day, I'll light a candle for you.
週日我也會來做彌撒
I'll even come to Mass on Sunday.
但你必須保護鎮上的瑪蓮娜·斯克迪亞
But you must protect Malena Scordia from the town.
對  就是那個寡婦  至少先照應幾年  然後我就會保護她
Yes, the widow... at least for a few years. Then I'll take over.
隨時為您效勞
I am always at your service.
- 再次慰問  瑪蓮娜  - 節哀
- Renewed condolences, Malena. - Condolences.
好一個美臀
What a piece of ass!
混小子
Son of a bitch!
小混蛋  給我回來
You little runt! Come back here!
- 你不能唱意大利語的歌曲嗎  - 你不能說德語嗎
- Can't you sing in Italian? - Can't you speak German?
雷納多  很晚了
Renato, It's late.
雷納多  起床
Renato, get up.
惡魔啊
Monster!
你是個戀物癖
You're a fetishist,
受虐狂  簡直是個變態
a sadomasochist, or even worse, a pervert!
- 那是什麼  - 法式的帽子  媽
- What is that? - It's just a French hat, Ma!
恥辱啊
Shame on you!
- 我能留著嗎  - 你這個不要臉的
- Can I keep them? - You shameless girl.
你看什麼看  走開
What are you looking at? Get out of here!
給我過來  混蛋
Come here, you little pig!
- 你個變態  - 我做什麼了
- Goddamn pervert! - What did I do?
以後不許跟我們坐一桌吃飯  聽見了嗎
You're not permitted to sit at the table with us, understand?
- 回答我  - 好吧
- Answer me! - Okay!
以後不許再跟你妹妹說話  聽見了嗎
You no longer have the right to speak to your sisters, understand?
把我鎖起來啊  你有本事來啊
Lock me up! I'll show you!
我沒改變主意前  你不准出屋子
You're not to leave this room until further notice!
兒子  好歹也喝點湯啊  對你有好處
Son, at least have some soup. It will do you good.
皮耶羅  他三天沒吃飯了
Pietro, he hasn't eaten for three days.
蘇聯人民從來不吃飯
In the Soviet Union, they never eat.
我說  這是什麼玩意
Still... What is this shit?
法西斯給的  至少看起來像咖啡
The Fascists gave it to us. At least it looks like coffee.
是啊  我看起來還像大導演維托裏奧·德·西卡呢
Sure, and I look like Vittorio De Sica.
他們給的東西都不好
Everything they give us is terrible!
看這些口袋  總是漏
Look at these pockets. They're always ripping open!
這些便宜的線根本就封不住口
This cheap thread doesn't hold the stitches!
不是線的問題
The thread isn't the problem!
我們的兒子背詩的時候  手也沒閒著
While our son recites poetry, his hands go to work in his pockets!
什麼意思
What does that mean?
現在明白了嗎
Do you get it now?
別補了  直接給封上吧
Just as well! Don't fix them. Sew the pockets closed!
那他就沒口袋了
But he'll have no pockets.
他會找到別的法子的  這是為了他好
He'll work it out. It will be good for his health!
關燈
Lights out!
疲憊的靈魂再也無法停泊在安逸的港灣
That the weary spirit may never repose in more restful harbor...
- 他發瘋了嗎  - 我看他是擼瞎了
- Has he gone crazy? - I think he's gone blind.
在女人前  你不安地坐著
While upon womens work you sat intent,
腦海中滿是迷茫的未來
content with the vague future you held in mind...
那五月的香氣  供你度過每一天
was the scented May, and thus you used to spend your days.
他需要透透氣
This child needs air.
- 透氣  - 對
- Air? - Air.
早上好  教授
Good morning, Professor.
這封信是給你的
This letter is for you.
說是急件
It says "urgent."
你丟盡了臉  你女兒瑪蓮娜把鎮上的男人睡了個遍
You're dishonored. Your daughter Malena is sleeping with the whole town.
是個匿名信  不過我看到了
It was an anonymous letter, but I read it!
說瑪蓮娜把鎮上的男人睡遍了
It says Malena is a whore with everyone in town!
那我們也有戲了
So there's hope for us too!
你收回那句話
Take it back!
信不信我打死你  短褲小子
I'll bust your ass, Mr. Short Pants!
今晚真美好
Tonight was wonderful.
- 我也覺得  - 我知道只過了十個月
- For me too. - I know it's been only ten months since.
- 但我能再見到你嗎  - 好吧  你贏了
- But maybe I can see you again. - All right. You win.
- 明天吧  - 好  只要我不用值班
- Tomorrow. - Okay, as long as I'm not on duty.
- 謝謝你的花  - 不客氣
- Thanks for the flowers. - You're welcome.
自己多保重
Take care of yourself.
那明天見
So see you tomorrow?
好
Yes.
- 再見  - 晚安  利昂
- Until then. - Good night, Leone.
明天幾點
What time?
- 晚上好  先生  - 晚上好個頭
- Good evening, sir. - Good evening, my ass!
你怎麼敢纏著我未婚妻
How dare you pester my fiancee!
一定是誤會  我是被邀請的
There must be a misunderstanding. I was invited.
你這個騙子  混蛋
You're a liar and a bastard!
我穿著制服  不能反擊  先生
Because I'm in uniform, I can not retaliate, sir.
- 但你最好乖乖的  - 去你的
- But you will answer to me. - Anytime.
- 懦夫  無賴  - 給我起來
- Coward, scoundrel! - Get up.
過來啊  看我不把你撕成兩半
Come here! I'll tear you apart, you coward!
撕成兩半
I'll break you in two!
放我走  要不我就不客氣了
Let me go! Or I'll have to get tough with you!
- 姦夫在這裏  - 老婆
- Here's the adulterer! - My wife!
- 長官  你看  他出軌了  - 跟一個男人
- Officer, look! He's cheating on me! - With a man?
跟一個叛徒
With a traitor!
你說就算有三米長的桿子也不碰她的
You said you wouldn't touch her with a ten-foot pole!
是牙醫
It's the dentist.
混蛋  我監視你很久了
I've been spying on you a long time, you bastard!
至於你
And as for you,
滾回你的鎮上去搶別人老公吧  婊子
go steal husbands from your own village, you whore!
我們知道她有情人  不過竟然有兩個
We knew she had one lover, but two?
牙醫是怎麼擠進去的
But where does the dentist fit in?
擠進她的腿咯
He fits in between her legs!
太丟臉了  她爸都辭掉了老師的工作
Her father was forced to quit the school in disgrace.
他再也不想見他女兒瑪蓮娜了
He never wants to see his daughter Malena again.
牙醫的老婆也把他踢出了家門
And the dentist's wife kicked him out of his house.
妻子一怒之下肯定會把他告上法庭
That dragon of a wife will drag him into court!
牙醫又有什麼錯呢  可憐的傢伙
What's the dentist got to do with it, poor guy?
是瑪蓮娜那個婊子  她才該被抓起來
Malena's the whore! She should be taken to court!
凱迪上尉看起來那麼正派
That Lt. Cadei seemed like such a gentleman.
怎麼摻合進來的
How could he get mixed up in this?
大家都知道她就是個小三
Everyone knows she's a home wrecker.
上尉自找的
The lieutenant was asking for it!
- 她都不是這兒的人  忘記了自己的地位  - 他們會上法庭嗎
- She's not from here. She forgets where she is. - Will they go to court?
當然了  她也許會坐牢的  他可是有婦之夫
Of course, she could go to jail. He's a married man!
牙醫頭上要縫三針呢
The dentist needed three stitches in his head.
但是牙醫先罵的上尉啊
But the dentist swore at the soldier first.
冒犯了長官
That's insulting an officer.
法庭會帶給我們答案的
We'll all end up in court!
當我們還在遠處看著她的時候
While we were watching her caboose,
中尉和牙醫已經跟她搞上了
the lieutenant and the dentist were riding the train!
她還去過律師跟公證人那兒
She's either going to the lawyer's or the notary's.
沒錯  但那兩個男人那麼老  她能幹嘛
Sure, but what will she do with two old men like them?
- 不好意思  - 請進
- Excuse me. - Come in.
需要幫助嗎
Can I help you?
我能和山托比律師談談嗎
May I speak to Lawyer Centorbi?
請坐
Please have a seat.
先生  寡婦斯克迪亞來了
Sir, it's the widow Scordia!
真的嗎  聖母啊
Can it be true? Beautiful Madonna!
讓她進來
Have her come in.
- 進去吧  - 謝謝
- Go in. - Thank you.
請坐
Please sit down.
真令人著迷
Charmed.
我們繼續聽瑪蓮娜·波西格諾的證詞
We now continue with the testimony of Maddalena Bonsignore,
寡婦斯克迪亞  又名瑪蓮娜
the widow Scordia called Malena.
她有可能會坐兩年牢
She could get two years in prison.
一切都會沒事的  相信我
Everything will be fine, trust me.
坐下
Sit down.
你被指控和牙醫加西帕·庫西馬諾
You're accused of involving Dr. Gaspare Cusimano...
保持地下戀人關係
in a secret and amorous relationship...
以達到破壞其家庭的目的
aimed at the breaking up of his family.
你認識牙醫庫西馬諾嗎
Do you know Dr. Cusimano?
是的
Yes.
你現在  或者之前  做過他的未婚妻嗎
Are you or have you ever... been his fiancee?
絕對不可能
Absolutely not.
我怎麼會跟有家室的男人訂婚呢
How could I be engaged to a married man?
為什麼庫西馬諾在那麼晚的時候
Why was Cusimano, at that unusual hour...
要去你家裏呢
on his way to your house?
我不知道
I don't know.
你們以前發生過夜晚共處的情況嗎
Had he been in your company on previous evenings?
是的  一次
Yes, once.
- 哪裏  - 在我家
- Where? - At my house.
他跳進來  看起來很蠢  但是
Jumped right in, the dentist did. He looks stupid, but...
- 他待了多久  - 不久
- How long did he stay? - Not long.
你們做了什麼
What did you do?
他給我帶了我父親的藥
He brought me some medicine for my father.
如果是你父親的藥  他為什麼要帶給你
If it was for your father, why did he bring it to you?
我不知道
I don't know.
他給你藥之後呢  你們又做了什麼
What did you do after he gave you the medicine?
他說了聲再見就走了
He said good-bye and left.
那為什麼庫西馬諾  這位曾經
Then why has Cusimano, are put able professional,
在五年前
who, five years ago...
給領袖拔過牙的資深牙科專家
had the honor of extracting one of II Duce's teeth...
在公眾場合聲稱他是你的未婚夫
publicly declare that he is your fiance?
他胡扯的  我跟這一點關係都沒有
He made that up. I had nothing to do with it.
你丈夫真膽大
Your husband's crazy.
你和凱迪中尉是什麼關係
What kind of relationship did you have with Lt. Cadei?
我是個寡婦  我和凱迪中尉的關係
I'm a widow. My business and that of Lt. Cadei...
跟法律無關
are no concern of the law.
好吧  你知道嗎
All right. Did you know that,
因為這些事情  凱迪中尉被發配到阿爾巴尼亞了
as a result of these affairs, Lt. Cadei was transferred to Albania?
幹掉了一個
One down.
在他離開之前  也接受了法庭的訊問
And before his departure, he was questioned in judicial inquiry.
讀給她聽
Clerk.
他聲稱他以前只在寡婦斯克迪亞家
He declared to have encountered
見過她兩次
the widow Scordia only twice... in her home,
並且沒有發生非正當關係
and to have had no amorous relationship...
他認為他們的關係  僅僅是普通朋友
considering their relationship "just a casual friendship."
賤人
Son of a bitch.
凱迪中尉收到了我的委託人的信件
Lt. Cadei was received by my client...
她毫不隱瞞她對中尉的
and she makes no secret about having had for him...
特殊感覺
certain feelings.
但不像已婚的庫西馬諾
But unlike the married Cusimano,
看看他吧  我就直說了
who was, let's face it, guilty...
看看這張因為縱慾過度而導致早衰
of a pre-senile dimming of the senses...
且寫滿罪惡的臉
of an intoxicating kaleidoscope of desires...
不像有家室的庫西馬諾
Unlike the family man Cusimano, But...
凱迪現在是
Cadei is...
以前也是
and was...
單身漢  一個單身漢
a bachelor... a bachelor!
聰明啊  那個律師
Clever, that lawyer.
他本身就是單身漢
He's a bachelor himself.
仔細調查就會發現事實真相  因此
Careful investigation of the facts tell us, therefore...
斯克迪亞沒有罪過
that the Scordia woman committed no other crime...
只有悲慘的命運
than that of being ill-fated,
孤獨又美麗
alone and beautiful.
她唯一的罪過便是  她的美麗
Here is her crime: Her beauty!
正因為如此  嫉妒
And from here, the envy,
謊言  恥辱
the lies, the disgrace,
使她一無所有  甚至剝奪了她父親的信任
that have deprived her even of a father's trust!
可是  她仍處在無聲的痛苦裏
And yet, she herself is still in silent agony...
向那遠在東非的戰死沙場之人的
mourning over that unmarked war grave...
無名墓冢哀悼
in faraway East Africa.
我們辯論的中心內容
In the beating heart of our argument...
是一個如此大膽卻又合情合理的觀點
is an audacious, but nonetheless valid, thesis...
我想請問
which asks just one question:
一個這樣的少婦
Can a young woman...
在愛的國度裏寡居了這麼久之後
after the odyssey of a widowhood endured for the love of country...
在新生活中尋求庇護有錯嗎
hope for protection in the shelter of a new life?
她難道沒有權利去追求  去譜寫
Does she have the right to yearn for, and to write...
一個屬於她的  全新的愛情故事嗎
a new ending to her own love story?
法官大人
Your Honor,
卡斯特庫托的居民們都回答  是的
the citizens of Castelcuto reply: "Yes!"
庫西馬諾不會再來煩我了吧
Will Cusimano leave me alone now?
當然不會  他被送進精神病院了
Of course. He's been put into a psychiatric clinic.
他要志願參加東非作戰
He wants to volunteer for the Forces in East Africa.
他還沒意識到我們幾年前就失去非洲了
He doesn't realize we lost Africa ages ago!
讓我們忘了庫西馬諾和凱迪中尉吧
But let's forget Cusimano and the fickle Lt. Cadei.
這兒只有我們
Let's get to us!
我知道這不多
I know it's not much.
但我只有這麼多了  他們剋扣了我的撫恤金
But it's all I have. They've cut my pension.
你不明白嗎
Don't you understand?
錢是小事
That's peanuts!
我的律師費遠不止這些
My fee is much more than that.
你永遠都付不起的
You'll never have enough money!
那我怎麼償還你
But how will I ever repay you?
很簡單  我的甜心
It's very easy, my sweet.
- 你說什麼  - 和我在一起  親愛的
- What are you saying? - Be with me, my love!
我好愛你啊
I'm in love with you!
在這艱難的年頭  一個女人不應該單身獨處
A woman shouldn't be alone during these hard times.
我有的是錢  你找不到更好的人了
I am a wealthy man. You won't find better.
我可以照顧你父親  你再也不用擔心了
I'll take care of your father. You'll never have to worry again.
我原諒她  她是為了付律師費
I forgive her. She did it to pay her lawyer's fees
但只此一次  下不為例
only once and never again.
但你沒有遵守我們的契約
But you didn't keep our agreement.
現在我們兩不相欠
Now we're even.
瑪蓮娜夫人  一個比我更有能力的人
Signora Malena, a more capable person than me...
寫過這樣一句話  真愛是不求回報的
wrote that the only truelove is unrequited love.
現在我懂了
Now I understand why.
離你上次出門已經很久了
It's been so long since you last came out of your house.
但分離的越久  我的愛就越深
But the longer we are apart, the stronger my love becomes.
他們說你要嫁給山托比律師
They say you're about to marry Centorbi, the lawyer.
我知道他們對你多惡劣
I know how badly they treat you here,
市場上的婆娘不賣食物給你
how the women in the market won't sell you any good food...
因為怕老婆  也沒有男人敢雇你
and no man would hire you for fear of his wife.
但是你怎麼能忍受一個又老又醜的人呢
But how will you manage to live with a fat, old man...
他醜到沒有一個姑娘願意和他在一起
so ugly that no girl ever wanted him?
他們說他從來不洗澡  渾身散發惡臭
They say he never washes and stinks like a goat.
你那白皙細膩的肌膚  怎麼能忍受
How will your smooth, white skin... bear rubbing against
那個臭男人的摩擦
the sweat of an old man...
更何況他還是個任憑母親使喚的  毫無主見的衰男
who never does anything without his mother's consent?
你們真的要結婚了嗎
Is it true you're getting married?
你在寫什麼
What are you writing?
給我  給我看看
Give me that! Let me see!
滾出去
Get out!
站直了
Stand up straight.
有點長啊  普拉西多先生
A little longer, Don Placido.
腰再做大一點  長大點還能穿
More room in the waist, for when he gets bigger.
明天可以做好嗎
Will they be ready tomorrow?
儘管我生意沒戰前好了  但也還是要時間的
The war has ruined my business, but it still takes time.
同盟國繼續轟炸
As Allied bombings continue.
等我一下
Wait for me.
天啊  求你幫幫我母親  求你了
Lord, help me with my mother, I beg you.
傻瓜  蠢貨
Moron! Idiot!
笨蛋
Idiot!
你不能再把我當小孩了  我長大了
You can't treat me like a child. I'm a grown man!
聽清楚了  你父親的名譽
Get this straight. Your father's good name...
可不能毀在那個婊子手裏
will never belong to that disgusting whore!
絕不可以
Never! Never!
絕不
Never!
律師算是擱一邊了
The lawyer was left high and dry!
他媽媽每週六還給他洗澡
His mother still bathes him every Saturday!
總是有人阻礙瑪蓮娜的工作
Malena always has someone throwing a wrench in the works!
找個男人取代律師又不難
It won't be hard finding someone to replace the lawyer!
- 過來 坐下  - 下一個人已經計劃出來了
- Come on, sit down. - The next in line already has a plan.
對  他的計劃在褲襠裏
Yeah, his plan is in his pants.
- 理發加修面  - 馬上來  先生
- A cut and shave. - Right away, sir.
早上好  安東尼奧
Good morning, Antonio.
我帶了些糖和麵粉
I brought some sugar and flour.
- 那麵包呢  - 最好的
- What about the bread? - The best.
- 我現在付不起  - 沒關係
- I can't pay right now. - That's no problem.
我保證能找到辦法讓你賺錢
I'm sure we can find a way to make you some money.
快點  這兒有人
Hurry, there's someone else over here!
是波西格諾教授
It's Professor Bonsignore.
瑪蓮娜的爸爸
Malena's father.
我是為你才來這兒
I'm here for you.
請節哀  斯克迪亞夫人
Condolences, Signora Scordia.
請節哀
Condolences.
讓開  小屁孩
Step aside, kid.
夫人  我們能些什麼呢  聽天由命吧
Signora, what can we do? We're in the Lord's hands.
考慮一下我的建議
Don't forget my offer.
- 是誰  - 我
- Who is it? - It's me.
- 那是誰  - 塞爾瓦托  是安東尼奧讓我來的
- Me who? - Salvatore. Antonio sent me.
我給你帶了些吃的
I brought you some more food.
進來吧
Come in.
- 你的秀髮美極了  - 你喜歡嗎
- Your hair looks terrific. - Do you like it?
- 是的  看起來更年輕  - 謝謝
- Yes, it makes you look younger. - Thank you.
我可以每週四都來
I can come every Thursday!
只要你帶食物過來
As long as you bring the food.
在我們的歷史上從來沒有想過聯合在一起
Never before in our history have we been called upon to band together.
幾年前元首還保證
Just a few years ago, II Duce promised
納粹絕對不會侵佔西西里
that the Nazis would never occupy Sicily.
你現在看  德國人到處都是
Look! The Germans are everywhere!
看那是誰
Look who's here.
她現在染了紅髮
She's a redhead now.
看她那騷樣
Look how she's put together.
真想把那頭髮剪了
I'd like to cut off that hair.
真噁心
How disgusting!
她現在竟然跟德國人搞了
Now she's even screwing the Germans.
- 那是誰  - 瑪蓮娜·斯克迪亞  婊子
- Who's that? - Malena Scordia, the slut.
她跟另一個妓女吉娜聯手了
She's teamed up with that other whore, Gina.
和德國人嗎
But with the Germans?
看來她們在邁得諾酒店裏做健身運動啊
Seems there are gymnastics at the Moderno Hotel.
兩個妓女從一間房跑到另一間房
The two whores run from room to room...
一次接一打德國軍官
servicing a dozen officers at a time.
爛貨
Holy shit!
大姐  這個小孩被魔鬼附身了
My good woman, this child is possessed by the devil!
耶穌  瑪利  約瑟保佑
Jesus, Mary and Joseph!
羅莎
Rosa!
走吧
Come here!
夠了
That's enough!
你看起來就像米開朗基羅畫的聖母憐子圖
It looks like you're posing for Michelangelo's Pieta of the poor!
不
No.
吾以耶穌基督之御名告知汝   不管汝欲藏於此身之何處  其形終現
Evil eye on blood is fed. Hold on fast till death is past.
當盡早脫離此身為宜  逃往他處
Exorcise the devil from this child.
不管汝藏於何處  盡早離開
Goat red, on wood fed, hold on fast.
以仁慈的聖靈之御名宣告
Head and tail, evil eye release this child.
神聖之體汝將永不得靠近  惡靈退散
Cast the devil into the wild.
真丟臉
Shameful!
可恥
Disgraceful!
他們用這法子把我叔叔治好了  他可得過霍亂
They cured my uncle this way... and he had cholera!
你兒子沒有病  他就快成為男人啦
Your son's not sick! He's becoming a man!
雞雞都這麼大了  他需要性生活
With a dick this big, he needs to fuck!
雷納多
Renato!
雷納多  在這等我
Renato, wait here for me.
過來  快點  把門關上
Come here. Come on. Close the door.
- 我爸爸呢  - 他來了
- My father? - He's coming.
姑娘們
Ladies!
選一個你喜歡的吧
Choose the one you like.
姑娘們
Ladies!
看這是誰在這啊
What do we have here?
小鮮肉哦
Fresh young meat.
洛佩塔  帶他上去吧
Lupetta, up to the room.
好好招待
Treat him right.
- 你叫什麼  - 雷納多·阿莫羅索
- What's your name? - Amoroso Renato.
阿莫羅索  真浪漫的名字
Amoroso. What a romantic name!
今晚我們不是被炸死就是進牢房
Tonight we either die in a bombing or end up in jail.
進去吧
Go ahead.
- 這是你的第一次嗎  - 不是
- Is it your first time? - No.
我在腦海裏做過無數次了
I've imagined it many times.
走  去給那個婊子一點教訓
Let's go give that shameless whore what she deserves.
退後  這是女人的事
Stay back. This is between the women.
你現在知道勾引我們的男人
Now you'll see what happens when you steal our men...
以及和猥瑣的德國人睡覺是什麼下場了吧
and sleep with the filthy Germans.
你今天賣春賣到頭了  婊子
It's the end of spreading your legs, whore!
現在來看看當婊子的下場
Now let's see what men make of you!
這個女人活該
The madame is served.
滾吧
Get lost!
消失吧
Disappear!
- 我認識那個人  - 誰啊
- I know that face. - Who is it?
尼諾·斯克迪亞  瑪蓮娜的丈夫
Nino Scordia, Malena's husband.
瑪蓮娜  那個和德國人搞的
Malena, the one who did it with the Germans.
可憐的傢伙  他死了更好
Poor guy. He was better off dead.
那不是瑪蓮娜的丈夫嗎
Isn't that Malena's husband?
嘿  喬瓦尼  來了個生人
Hey, Giovanni, there's a strange guy.
你認識瑪蓮娜·斯克迪亞嗎
Do you know Malena Scordia?
她是誰
Who's she?
你是誰  這是我家的房子
Who are you? This is my family's house!
我們什麼都不知道
We don't know anything.
我們來的時候  這裏已經沒人住了
When we came, no one was living here.
一個人都沒有嗎
No one?
可憐的傢伙  沒人會把事實告訴他的
Poor guy. No one will tell him the truth.
你怎麼說  我聽說你老婆做妓女了
What would you say, "I hear your wife is a prostitute"?
聽說她屁股還是很翹
I hear she's still a great piece of ass.
我斷了個胳膊  我又沒死
I lost an arm. I wasn't dead!
然後我被俘虜到印度並且得了瘧疾  告訴他
Then I was taken prisoner in India and I contracted malaria. Tell him.
先生  他丟了條胳膊
Sir, he lost his arm...
嘿  哪裏的孩子  在這幹嘛  快走
Hey, kid, what are you doing here? Go away.
我是服務生  咖啡
Me "boy-bar." Coffee.
我來收咖啡杯  懂嗎
I have to get the coffee cups. Understand?
好的  好的
Okay, alright.
我家人世世代代生活在鎮上
My family has lived in this town for generations.
現在沒人願意跟我說話
Now no one will talk to me.
家也成了難民營  老婆也不見了
My house is a refugee camp, and my wife has disappeared.
鎮上沒人知道她在哪裏
No one in town knows where she is.
他老婆就是那個女人
His wife was the woman
就是我們來這裏的時候看到被打的那個
we saw beaten up on the day we arrived here.
人人都說她是妓院裏的妓女
Everybody says she's a prostitute in a whorehouse.
幫我找到她  我想帶她回家
Help me find her. I want to bring her home.
你好  你不記得我了嗎  我是尼諾·斯克迪亞
Excuse me. Don't you remember me? I'm Nino Scordia.
- 你認錯人了  - 能借個火嗎
- You mistake me for someone else. - Could I have a light?
你是法西斯的秘書  你是他的代理人
You were the Fascist secretary, and you were his deputy.
幫我個忙  知不知道我老婆到底怎麼了
You can help me. Do you know what happened to my wife?
她沒有加入共產黨嗎
Didn't she join the Communist Party?
她有張摟著共產黨頭目的照片
She was photographed with her arms around the Commie leader.
你們一家都是英雄
You're a family of heroes!
沒錯
You're right.
那些為你們這些混蛋戰鬥的人不是英雄
Those who fought the war for you bastards aren't heroes.
去西西里的妓院逛逛吧
Go take a walk through the brothels of Sicily.
說不定能找到你老婆
You may find your wife there!
等等  回來
Wait a minute. Come back!
親愛的斯克迪亞閣下
Dear Signor Scordia,
原諒我沒有勇氣面對面告訴你
forgive me if I don't have the courage to speak man to man.
這幾個月我學會了勇敢  雖然只有一點點
These last months have taught me much about courage, even if I have found little myself.
我是唯一知道你妻子真相的人
I'm the only one who knows the truth about your wife.
這裏的人都只說她的壞話
Around here, they only say bad things about her.
但相信我  你的妻子瑪蓮娜對你很忠誠
But believe me, your wife Malena was faithful to you.
你是她唯一愛過的人  這是絕對真實的
You are the only man she loved. This is the honest truth.
當然事實是發生了許多事情
It is true, a lot of things happened,
但那時候  你已經死了很久了
but back then, you had been dead along time.
我最後一次見到她的時候  她在去墨西拿的火車上
The last time I saw her, she was on a train for Messina.
我本應該像所有的匿名信一樣  署名  一個朋友
I should sign "a friend," like all anonymous letters,
但我叫雷納多
but my name is Renato.
一年後
One Year Later
早上好  法官
Good morning, Judge.
都很好  謝天謝地
All is well, thank God.
把它吃光  小甜心
Eat up, my sweet pea.
- 我操  - 看誰來了
- Sons of bitches! - Look who's here!
喬治奧  看誰來了
Giorgio, look who's here!
你們為什麼都看那個女人
Why are you all looking at that woman?
沒什麼
It's nothing.
我在廣場上看到他們了  挽著胳膊走的
I saw them in the square. They were walking arm in arm.
安靜點  她在這
Quiet. She's here!
這得多大勇氣才敢回來
It took a lot of courage to come back.
看那是誰
Look who's here.
我聽說了  但我不信
I heard it, but I didn't believe it.
- 他們非得看些什麼  - 他們應該隨她一個人去
- What have they got to look at? - They should leave her in peace.
她眼角多了些皺紋
She's got some wrinkles around her eyes.
也胖了些
She's put on weight, too.
但她還是很漂亮
But she's still beautiful.
早上好  斯克迪亞夫人
Good morning, Mrs. Scordia.
早上好
Good morning.
來點西紅柿嗎  這邊便宜些
Want some nice tomatoes? They cost less over there.
- 早上好  - 謝謝
- Good morning. - Thank you.
超值特賣
Nice things here!
- 喜歡嗎  瑪蓮娜夫人  - 嗯
- Like it, Signora Malena? - Yes.
- 試試看  - 不用的  可以了
- Try it on. - No, that's okay.
- 沒問題的  - 下次吧
- It's no problem. - Another time.
把包給我  待會再說
Give me your bag. We'll discuss it later.
- 謝謝  - 好運
- Thank you. - Good day.
沒事  我可以的
It's okay. I'll get it.
謝謝
Thank you.
謝謝幫忙
Thank you for your help.
好運  瑪蓮娜夫人
Good luck, Signora Malena.
我盡可能快地騎起腳踏車
I pedaled as fast as I could
好像要逃離一樣
as if I were escaping...
逃離渴望  逃離純真  逃離她
from longing, from innocence, from her.
時光飛逝  我也愛過了很多女人
Time has passed, and I have loved many women.
她們都緊緊抱住我
And as they've held me close...
問我是不是會記得她們
and asked if I will remember them,
我會說  是的  我會記得你
I've said, "Yes, I will remember you."
但我唯一無法忘記的人  只有從未問過我的
But the only one I've never forgotten is the one who never asked...
瑪蓮娜
Malena.
導 演
朱 塞 佩 · 托 納 多 雷
主 演
莫 妮 卡 · 貝 魯 奇
圭 塞 佩 · 蘇 爾 法 羅
配 樂
埃 尼 奧 · 莫 裏 康 內
劇 終
THE END